Email: javed.sial91@gmail.com https://github.com/javi-99 Mobile: +92-322-4350928

Personal Statement

A researcher with a proven history of problem-solving and meeting project deadlines. Being equipped with a theoretical and practical understanding of signal processing, machine learning & deep learning, by undertaking in-depth studies including the identification & modification of state of the art, I can believe out of the box for tailored alternatives.

EXPERIENCE

• Information Technology University

Lahore, Pakistan

Research Associate at Blockchain Lab

Jul. 2019 - Present

- O Supervisor: Dr. Ali Ahmed, POSTDOC MIT, USA
- Conduct research and leading projects with a focus on applications of machine learning & deep learning in Blockchain Technology

• Information Technology University

Lahore, Pakistan

Research Assistant & Industrial Collaborator at SPIDER Lab

Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2019

- O Supervisor: Dr. Ali Ahmed, POSTDOC MIT, USA
- o Conducted research with a focus on applications of signal processing, machine learning & deep learning in fault diagnosis and prognosis of mechanical machinery.
- I led & implemented the allocated projects in the industry as part of a cooperation between industry and the SPIDER Lab.

SUPARCO

Lahore, Pakistan

Sub-Engineer (Communication Satellite)

Oct. 2011 - Oct. 2017

• Conducted trend analysis and anomaly detection in the telemetries of satellite subsystems.

EDUCATION

• Information Technology University (ITU)

Lahore, Pakistan

Master of Science in Electrical Engineering

Sept. 2017 - Aug. 2019

o Thesis: Fault Diagnosis & Prognosis of Rotating Machinery using Vibration Signal Analysis

o Advisor: Dr. Ali Ahmed, POSTDOC MIT, USA

• Research Lab: SPIDER lab WEBPAGE

o Focus: Signal Processing & Machine Learning in Industrial Informatics

Selected Courses: Advanced Digital Signal Processing, Machine Learning, Advanced Mathematics

• University of Central Punjab (UCP)

Lahore, Pakistan

o Project: Design & Implementation of Octocopter 2013 - 2017

o Advisor: Dr. Ali Nasir, Phd university of michigan, usa

o Focus: Control System & Signal Processing

• SUPARCO Institute of Technical Training (SITT)

Bachelor of Science in Electrical Engineering; GPA: 3.50

Karachi, Pakistan

Diploma of Associate Engineer (DAE) in Electronics; Score: 83%

2008 - 2011

SKILLS & EXPERTISE

I spend most of my time with scikit-learn, keras, tensorflow and pytorch (equally proficient) in python. My ability set includes comprehension and implementation of the recent research papers related to my field, feature selection & pre-processing, scientific computing and technical writing. My skill set for technology involves but is not restricted to the following:

• Tensorflow • Python • Numpy • R, bnlearn C++

Pytorch
Scikit-learn
Pandas
Matlab,

Projects

• Open Source

o GearBox Faults Detection using SincNet Architecture

CODE

Fault diagnosis and prognosis of an industrial gearbox with SincNet architecture (A deep learning model)where the first layer have of CNN is modified using DSP tools to make human interpretation

o Predicting Faulty Regime of Train Car (phm2017)

CODE

A PCA based anomaly detection technique to identify the faulty suspensions of a train bogie.

• Pruning of Deep Neural Networks using Convex Optimization

CODE

Formulated into a convex problem and solved using Keras with tensorflow & cvxpy to significantly sparse the weight matrix with accuracy score of 0.84.

• Industry Projects

o Vibration Sensor Data Validation

INTECH

Designed a complete solution to validate the time series vibration data of sensors mounted with different methods. The solution is based on intelligent feature selection utilizing DSP tools and training the discriminative classifiers to detect the fault in the sensor mounting.

• Hardware & Front-end Software Interface

SpaceTech Engineering Consultants

Designed electronic hardware and software interface of prototype turbines for a Hydraulics & Fluid Mechanics Lab. I successfully performed hardware calibration, developed codes/algorithms to display the required parameters in window application.

Research

In progress

- LSTM with Wavelets Based Vibration Signal Processing for Fault Detection of a Gearbox. **Javed Ahmad** and A. Ahmed. Have to Submit in *IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics*, 2019.
- Learning of Faults in rotating machinery using SincNet. **Javed Ahmad**, F. Shamshad and A. Ahmed. Have to submit in *Machine Learning and the Physical Sciences*, *Workshop*, *NeurIPS*, 2019.

Rewards & Honors

- Awarded Graduate Research Fellowship in ITU for my academic performance.
- Awarded Gold Medal for getting first position in the annual exhibition of final year projects at UCP.
- Dean's Honor roll for 1-2 semester during my BS.
- First position all over Pakistan in Robo-Sprint competition 2014.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• Teaching Assistant for Machine Learning

Information Technology University, Lahore.

• Teaching Assistant for Power System Analysis

Information Technology University, Lahore.

• Teaching Assistant for Calculus and Analytical Geometry

Information Technology University, Lahore.

ACADEMIC REFERENCES

• Dr. Ali Ahmed

Assistant Professor, Dept. of Electrical Engineering Information Technology University, Lahore ali.ahmed@itu.edu.pk

• Dr. Mahboob Ur Rehman

Assistant Professor, Dept. of Electrical Engineering Information Technology University, Lahore mahboob.rahman@itu.edu.pk

• Dr. Ali Nasir

HOD, Dept. of Electrical Engineering University of Central Punjab, Lahore a.nasir@ucp.edu.pk